Inventory of the James Robert Huntley papers
Hoover Institution Archives
James Robert Huntley papers
1938-2010
81071
Hoover Institution Archives
365 manuscript boxes, 5 card file boxes (148.2 linear feet)
Diaries, writings, correspondence, reports, notes, meeting materials, resolutions, statements, and printed matter relating to political, economic and cultural relations among Atlantic community countries and Japan, and private promotion of international cooperation, international education, and international environmental protection.
Huntley, James Robert.
Access
Collection is open for research. Collection stored off site; a minimum of two days notice is required for use. Boxes may be requested through Stanford's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives between 1981 and 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Atlantic Council of the United States records, Hoover Institution Archives
Committee for a Community of Democracies--USA records, Hoover Institution Archives
W. Randolph Burgess papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1923 Born, Tacoma, Washington
1948 B.A., University of Washington
1949-1951 Consultant, Washington Parks Recreation Commission, Olympia, Washington
1952-1954 Exchange of persons officer, United States Foreign Service, Frankfurt, Nuremberg, Germany
1954-1955 Director of cultural center, United States Information Agency, Hof an der Saale, Germany
1956 M.A., international relations, Harvard University
1956-1958 European regional affairs officer, United States Information Agency, Washington, D.C.
1958-1960 Deputy public affairs officer, United States Mission to European Communities, Brussels, Belgium
1959 Member to the United States delegation to the Atlantic Congress, London, England
1960-1964 Secretary, Education Committee, NATO Parliamentarians Conference, Brussels, Belgium
1960-1965 Executive secretary and director, Atlantic Institute
1965 Author, The NATO Story
1965-1967 Program associate, International Affairs Division, Ford Foundation, New York City, New York
1967-1968 Secretary general, Atlantic College
1968-1974 Writer, consultant, and lecturer on international affairs, Guildford, England
1969-1974 Board of directors, International Standing Conference on Philanthropy
1970 Author, with Warren Randolph Burgess, Europe and America: The Next Ten Years
1970s Consultant, Wells Management Consultants Ltd.
1971 Author, Man's Environment and the Atlantic Alliance
1974-1983 Research fellow and senior advisor to president on international affairs, Battelle Memorial Institute, Seattle, Washington
1976-1994 Member, Association to Unite Democracies (formerly Federal Union, Inc.)
1979-1992 Founding chairman, Committees for a Community of Democracies
1980 Author, Uniting the Democracies: Institutions of the Emerging Atlantic-Pacific System
Circa 1980 Author, World Politics in the 1980s
1983-1985 President, Atlantic Council of the United States
1985-1989 Consultant, University of South Carolina
1987-1991 Co-founder, 21st Century Foundation
1998 Author, Pax Democratica: A Strategy for the 21st Century
1999-2007 Vice president, Council for a Community of Democracies
2006 Author, An Architect of Democracy: Building a Mosaic of Peace
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of James Robert Huntley include diaries, writings, correspondence, reports, notes, meeting materials, resolutions, statements, and printed matter related to political, economic and cultural relations among Atlantic community countries and Japan, and private promotion of international cooperation, international education, and international environmental protection.
During his youth, Huntley was concerned with a shift in world politics towards dictatorships and war. After studying international relations at the University of Washington, he accepted an appointment with the United States Foreign Service in 1952. He was stationed in Germany, involved in democratic education and the solidification of German and United States relations. In 1960, Huntley left the United States Foreign Service to found the Atlantic Institute in Paris, a think tank created to study the problems of Allied cooperation and conflict.
In 1974, Huntley accepted a research fellowship at the Battelle Memorial Institute, traveling to Europe, Canada, Japan, Australia, and New Zealand to study the Atlantic-Pacific system. While in this role, he authored World Politics in the 1980s, which was printed privately for Battelle's corporate clients. Correspondence, project proposals, and other materials related to the Battelle Memorial Institute can be found throughout the collection.
Throughout his career, Huntley founded organizations for furthering democracy and the Atlantic community, including the Mid-Atlantic Clubs, the Standing Conference of Atlantic Organizations, the Consortium for Atlantic-Pacific Affairs (CAPA), and the International Standing Conference on Philanthropy (INTERPHIL). He also served in leadership roles for many such organizations, including as president of the Atlantic Council of the United States. In 1979, Huntley co-founded the Committees for a Community of Democracies (CCD), a group committed to strengthening relationships among democracies. In 1992, the Association to Unite the Democracies embarked on the Next Century Initiative (NCI), which was based on the ideas of the Committees for a Community of Democracies and involved many of its early members. The NCI became incorporated as a separate group, eventually becoming the Council for a Community of Democracies. The collection documents Huntley's involvement in these organizations through correspondence, meeting minutes, and extensive notes Huntley wrote about his career.
Huntley kept a diary spanning more than fifty years of his life. His diary entries begin in 1952, the year he was hired by the United States Foreign Service. These diaries, along with a draft of his memoirs, can be found in box 24.
The collection also includes Huntley's speeches and writings concerning democracy, the Atlantic community, international education, and Japan. In 1998, Huntley authored Pax Democratica, in which he argued that democratic countries should work together to create a more peaceful world. Drafts of this book and of other influential works, such as Uniting the Democracies, can be found throughout the collection.
Huntley was interested in international education, writing many articles on the subject. Materials on international education include networking dossiers, documenting Huntley's interaction with various education organizations. The collection also includes files containing materials related to non-governmental organizations, which contain questionnaires recording basic information about the organizations, descriptions of their activities, and use of budgets.
Index of Major Groups
The collection has not been physically arranged. Most materials fall into the following groups.
71-73, 212 21st Century Foundation file
73-77, 139, 209 Association to Unite the Democracies (formerly Federal Union) file
228-231, 251-253 Atlantic Community file
123-125 Atlantic Council of the United States (ACUS) file
2-7, 13, 20-23, 86-87 Battelle Memorial Institute. Includes materials on the Battelle Seminar and Study Program and Advanced International Systems file
287, 316, 341, 366 Biographical file
24, 32, 69, 81-86, 100-102, 322 Committees for a Community of Democracies file
66-68, 96-99, 288-289, 310-311 Consortium for Atlantic-Pacific Affairs (CAPA) file
15, 29, 46-48, 91-93, 199-201, 261-263, 344 Correspondence
24 Diaries
4, 225-228 Environment and ecology file
269-272 Foundations and philanthropy file
62-65 INTERPHIL file
31-32, 39 Japan file
118-122, 220, 317-321 Next Century Initiative (NCI) and Council for a Community of Democracies file
50-58, 108-116, 180-184, 214-215, 304-305 Non-governmental organizations (NGOs) file
33, 335-339 Note cards
27, 31, 35-37, 43-45, 48, 147-153, 176, 232, 237-244 Printed matter
1, 6-14, 16-17, 127, 130-132, 211-213, 277-278, 291, 341, 348-355, 370 Speeches and writings
79 United States Information Agency (USIA) file
Associations, institutions, etc.; Environmental protection.; Intellectual cooperation.; International cooperation.; International economic relations.; International education.; International relations.; United States--Foreign relations--Europe.; Europe--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Japan.; Japan--Foreign relations--United States.; Atlantic Institute for International Affairs.; Atlantic Council of the United States.; Council for a Community of Democracies.
- Foundation for the Cohesion of the West, correspondence, 1984 (Box 1)
- Writings by Huntley
  - "The Atlantic Institute: Early Days," draft and correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - "Private Initiatives and the Cohesion of the Western Democracies," Part I to II, 1983 May (Box 1)
- Atlantic Institute, undated (Box 1)
- Battelle Seminar and Study Program/Advanced International Systems
  - Conferences, seminars, and educational projects
    - Professor Frank Munk, 1975 September 22 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Ambassador Robert Neumann, 1975 October 23-24 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Switzerland, "The Future Is Our Concern,", 1975 October 4-7 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Outside sponsors (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Federal Union, 1981 January-February (Box-folder 2: 5-9)
  - Rainier Bank Overseas Branch Heads, 1976 July-August (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Rainier Club Lyceum, 1976 September 21 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Washington Council on International Trade, University of Washington, 1976 November 24 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Miscellaneous education projects, outside sponsors (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Rainier bank executive, 1982 September 9 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Bowaters, 1976 July-September (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Bank of California, 1976 July (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Weyerhaeuser, 1976 October (Box-folder 2: 17)
- Miscellaneous education projects, Whitman College International Committee, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 18)
- Advanced International School- The Fuji School, King-FM Interview with Ancil Payne, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 19)
- Battelle Seminar and Study Program/Advanced International Systems
  - Grant proposals, 1975 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Kudos, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Huntley consulting activities, U.S. government (Box-folder 2: 22)
- Education and international communication
  - International Communications Agency, 1978 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Norway and America exchange, 1977 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Centre International de Formation Européenne, 1975 April (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - International communication and interaction, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Mid-America programs (James Becker), 1975 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - College of Europe, 1973-1980 (Box-folder 3: 6-7)
  - Regional Council for International Education, 1974 October 3 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - John Hopkins Bologna Centre, 1972-1978 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - J.F.K. Center, Tillburg University, 1976-1981 (Box-folder 3: 10-11)
  - International Studies Association, 1975 April (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - International Baccalaureate, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Institute of International Education (Box-folder 3: 14)
- Hoover-Germany Project, 1982 January-March (Box-folder 3: 15)
- Battelle Seminar and Study Program/Advanced International Systems
  - Monograph, House of Representatives Testimony, Atlantic Convention, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - "The Global Significance of the Atlantic Pacific System,", 1978 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - "Japan in International Society of the Future,", 1976 December (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - "Historic Origins of the Atlantic System,", 1976 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Cultural handbooks, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 3: 20)
- Battelle Memorial Institute budgets, 1974-1978 (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Battelle Memorial Institute, 1977 January 18 (Box-folder 4: 2)
- International relations, futurism, 1979 July 3 (Box-folder 4: 3)
- Environment and ecology
  - Battelle pamphlet, 1971 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - U. N. articles, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) articles, 1979 May 5 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - NATO articles, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - EEC articles, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Council of Europe, 1974 October 10 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - International, Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) article, 1975 January 14 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - France article, 1975 May 20 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Transport, 1975-1981 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Population, 1975-1982 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Environmental pollution, 1975-1981 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Sea use and planning, 1978-1982 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Land use planning, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Housing and urban development, 1976 March (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Historic and cultural, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Food, 1975-1982 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Environmental energy and resources, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 4: 20-22)
  - General, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Bibliography, 1971-1981 (Box-folder 4: 24)
- Education and International Institutions, Australian Administrative Staff College, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 4: 25)
- Battelle Seminar and Study Program/Advanced International Systems
  - Purchasing (books, etc.), 1974-1977 (Box-folder 5: 1-3)
  - Budgets, reporting, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 5: 4-7)
  - Battelle Institute, S&HA budget, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 5: 8-9)
  - Plans, 1975-1982 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - S&HA, Huntley advisory activities, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Behavioral and social sciences, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Science and Human Affairs Program, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Project proposals, 1974 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - R.W. Dayton and C.W. Kern correspondence, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Policy and plans, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 5: 16-17)
- Uniting the Democracies, marketing and promotion, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 6: 1-4)
- Battelle Seminar and Study Program/Advanced International Systems
  - Research plans and outlines, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Research projects, 1975 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Administration, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Personnel, Martha Darling, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Personnel, Toshio Nishi, 1975 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Personnel, John Teal, 1976 May-June (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Computerizing, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 6: 11)
- Uniting the Democracies
  - Early marketing and promotion, 1976-1983 (Box-folder 6: 12-15)
  - Battelle Seminar and Study Program/Advanced International Systems file, 1977-1982 (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
  - Reactions, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 7: 3)
- Battelle Seminar and Study Program/Advanced International Systems
  - Evidence of effectiveness, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Responses to 1975 research outline (Box-folder 7: 5-7)
- Uniting the Democracies, indexing, proofing, permissions to quote, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 7: 8-10)
- Battelle Seminar and Study Program/Advanced International Systems, 1975 and 1976 Research Outlines, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7: 11)
- Writings of Huntley
  - Correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Documents for education (documents pour l'enseignement), 1974 February-May (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Articles, drafts, 1964-1978 (Box-folder 8: 3-4)
  - Drafts, letters, 1969-1976 (Box-folder 8: 5)
- Senator Percy Memo, 1981 January 28 (Box-folder 8: 6)
- James Robert Huntley "Multithink" BMI Notes, 1980 (Box-folder 8: 7)
- Writings of Huntley
  - "Uniting the Democracies," fifth draft, 1979 February 15 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - "Towards a Community of Democracies," pamphlet, 1982 February (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - "Uniting the Democracies," flyer (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - Atlantic Convention Resolution, 1975 September 8 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - World Survey No. 41: "Food From the Sea,", 1972 May (Box-folder 8: 12)
    Scope and Contents note
    Atlantic Education Trust publication.
  - The World and the School, No. 18, 1980 January (Box-folder 8: 13)
    Atlantic Information Centre for Teachers publication.
  - The World and the School: "European Security," No. 22, 1971 May (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - "Teaching about Collective Security and Conflict,", 1971 October (Box-folder 8: 15)
    Atlantic Information Centre for Teachers publication, edited by Huntley.
  - "Teaching about the American Impact on Europe,", 1969 November (Box-folder 8: 16)
  - "Man's Environment and the Atlantic Alliance,", 1972 October (Box-folder 8: 17)
    NATO Information Service publication.
  - "Western Europe and the United States: Toward New Transatlantic Educational Relationships,", 1970 September (Box-folder 8: 18)
  - "The Atlantic Colleges: A New Concept in Education," pamphlet, 1968 (Box-folder 8: 19)
  - "International Educational and Cultural Exchange,", 1967 (Box-folder 8: 20)
    Publication, includes article by Huntley.
  - Orbis: Quarterly Journal of World Affairs, Vol. X, No. 1, 1966 (Box-folder 8: 21)
  - "The Balance of Power in Europe Since the Invasion of Czechoslovakia,", 1969 (Box-folder 8: 22)
    Contributions by Huntley.
  - NATO Hikayesi, 1969 (Box-folder 8: 23)
    Turkish edition.
  - "The NATO Story,", 1969 (Box-folder 8: 24)
- Assorted contacts and membership lists, 1969 October-November (Box-folder 9: 1)
- Karlheinz Koppe, "Account of a Journey,", 1969 October (Box-folder 9: 2)
- Notes and articles concerning U.S.-Canada issues, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  Most likely collected for North American Review.
- Correspondence concerning North American Review, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 9: 4)
- Speeches and writings of Huntley
  - Presentations on "Youthful Unrest" and "The Revolt of Youth,", 1969-1970 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    Lecture also titled "Youth and the Atlantic Community."
  - Notes, interviews, and outlines for "Youthful Unrest,", 1969-1970 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Correspondence concerning "Youthful Unrest,", 1969-1970 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Collected articles concerning nominations and appointments, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Speech at the Hague on NATO and the environment, 1970 April-May (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - Class, lecture, and speech notes, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - "The Revolt of Youth" publications, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - "The Transatlantic Agenda,", 1970-1974 (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - Speeches on the environmental crisis, 1971 March-April (Box-folder 9: 13)
  - Man's Environment and the Atlantic Alliance publications, 1971 March-June (Box-folder 9: 14)
  - Centre Universitaire des Hautes Etudes Européennes, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 9: 15)
  - "The Pound in Your Pocket," speech, National Council of Social Science, 1971 October-December (Box-folder 9: 16)
  - Notes and writings on environmental topics, 1972 March-May (Box-folder 9: 17)
- Assorted resumes, curricula vitae, and biographical sketches, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 9: 18)
- Obituaries and correspondence, 1970-1976 (Box-folder 9: 19)
- Correspondence, 1968 (Box-folder 10: 1)
- The NATO Story
  - Notes and material, 1949-1969 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Publications, 1965 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 10: 4-9)
  - Drafts and notes, 1968 (Box-folder 10: 10)
- Conferences and panels, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 10: 11)
- Articles on NATO and French economy, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 10: 12)
- Correspondence, 1969 (Box-folder 10: 13)
- Articles, pamphlets, and flyers, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 10: 14)
- Correspondence, 1970 (Box-folder 10: 15)
- National Assembly for Social Policy and Development, 1970 (Box-folder 10: 16)
- Appointments and itineraries, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 10: 17)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 10: 18)
- European Federalist Party letters and documents, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 10: 19)
- Groupe D'Action documents, 1971 January (Box-folder 10: 20)
- "Americans in Britain" proposals, 1971 May (Box-folder 10: 21)
- Flow plan brochure, 1972 May (Box-folder 10: 22)
- Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 10: 23)
- Publications on international education, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 11: 1)
- Regional Council for International Education
  - Background information, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - Presidents' mission notes, 1970 January-April (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - Itineraries, 1970 January-March (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Correspondence, reports, and proposals, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - Academic Program in Western Europe and Atlantic Studies, 1971 (Box-folder 11: 6)
- Speeches and writings of Huntley
  - The World and the School, 1970 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Speech and seminar notes, 1970 (Box-folder 11: 8)
  - "The United States and the European Community", 1970-1973 (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - "Uniting the Democracies," 6th draft
    - Acknowledgements, forward, preface, Chapters 1-3, 1979 June (Box-folder 11: 10)
    - Chapters 4-6, 1979 June (Box-folder 11: 11)
    - Chapter 7, Appendices, 1979 June (Box-folder 11: 12)
- European Cultural Foundation, annual report, 1968 (Box-folder 12: 1)
- American universities field staff consulting, 1968-1972 (Box-folder 12: 2)
- Correspondence concerning proposed projects and employment, 1968-1972 (Box-folder 12: 3-4)
- Source Book on the Atlantic Community, notes and correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 12: 5)
- "Letter From Europe" radio program, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 12: 6)
- Business management articles, 1971 (Box-folder 12: 7)
- Consulting work, correspondence with Frank Wells (Wells Management Consultants Ltd.), 1970-1973 (Box-folder 12: 8-9)
- Ironbridge Gorge Museum Trust, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 12: 10)
- Consulting work, correspondence with Frank Wells (Wells Management Consultants Ltd.), 1974 (Box-folder 12: 11)
- Report and correspondence, European Cultural Foundation, "Europe 2000" Project, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 12: 12)
- "The Citizen and the City in the Year 2000,", 1969-1970 (Box-folder 12: 13)
- European Cultural Foundation bulletins, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 12: 14)
- Speeches and writings
  - Book ideas and notes, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 12: 15)
  - Speeches in Italy, 1972 May-August (Box-folder 12: 16)
  - Sixth International Investment Symposium, 1972 June (Box-folder 12: 17)
  - "Atlantic Commentary" prospectus, 1972 August (Box-folder 12: 18)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1972 October (Box-folder 12: 19)
  - Neue Zürcher Zeitung article, 1973 (Box-folder 12: 20)
  - The Western World publication, 1974 February-April (Box-folder 12: 21)
  - Materials and draft of Introduction to Europe, 1974 April (Box-folder 12: 22)
  - "General Social and Economic Analysis of Britain Today" (Box-folder 12: 23)
  - Wells Group and other professional fundraisers, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 12: 24)
  - The Atlantic System in the 1970s, drafts and notes, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - "Proposed New Journal on Protozoology,", 1969 April (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - German and French material on European Party and Union, 1969 (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - The European-Atlantic Movement (T.E.A.M.) lectures at Oxford on youth, 1970 August (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - "A Study of Gaps" and "Gaps in the Future,", 1969-1970 (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - Articles and lectures on environment and pollution issues, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - IBM World Trade Education Center: "Youth,", 1971 (Box-folder 13: 7)